Guide to the The Womxn Project records 1980-2019 (bulk 2017-2019)
Brown University Library
The Womxn Project records
1980-2019
(bulk 2017-2019)
Ms.2020.001
John Hay Library University Archives and Manuscripts Box A Brown University Providence, RI, 02912 Telephone: Manuscripts: 401-863-3723; University Archives: 401-863-2148 Email: Manuscripts: hay@brown.edu; University Archives: archives@brown.edu
6.25 linear feet (2 file boxes, 2 oversize boxes, and 1 shoebox)
The Womxn Project
The Womxn Project is a non-profit organization in Rhode Island focused on building a strong, feminist, community-based movement to further human rights of Rhode Islanders by using art and activism to advance education and social change. The Womxn Project stirs social awareness and invites political action to inclusively further womxn’s rights through creative advocacy campaigns and collaborative art projects. This collection contains records and items that were created to advocate for the passing of the Reproductive Privacy Act in 2019. Materials include canvassing packets, memorabilia, handmaid’s costumes worn at lobbying events at the Rhode Island Statehouse, community petition quilt squares, the community petition quilt, and petition scrolls that predated the quilt. Materials date from 1980-2019, though the bulk of the collection dates from 2017-2019.
Biographical/Historical Note
The Womxn* Project is a non-profit organization in Rhode Island focused on building a strong, feminist, community-based movement to further human rights of Rhode Islanders by using art and activism to advance education and social change. The Womxn Project stirs social awareness and invites political action to inclusively further womxn’s rights through creative advocacy campaigns and collaborative art projects.
In 2017, Jocelyn Foye, Jordan Hevenor, Sarah Markey, Andrea Preisch, and Mara Trachtenberg co-organized The Womxn Project in response to the election of President Donald Trump and a lecture series started at Hera Gallery called Creating Together. The group formed around a passion for womxn’s rights and the goal to preserve safe and legal access to abortion in Rhode Island. With the potential overturning of the federal Roe legislation, each state’s laws would dictate what happened to abortion access.
Combining their collective skills in grassroots activism and artistic creativity, they started hosting meetings at the Hera Gallery in South Kingstown, Rhode Island - one of the earliest women's cooperative galleries in the United States and now the fifth oldest. The outpouring of interest showed that Rhode Island womxn were interested in collectively working together to secure this right, one that had been tried for 24 years prior.
The Womxn Project found artistic ways to advocate for the passing of the Reproductive Privacy Act, originally referred to Reproductive Health Care Act, which was signed into law on June 10, 2019. These artistic activist projects, called artivism, included handwritten petitions scrolls, projections on the State House, a performative reading of the federal Roe legislation, and later the Community Petition Quilt to name a few. With the Community Petition Quilt, constituents could sign and decorate a square in support of the acts and the squares were then sewn together to create panels for a quilt that grew in size as they acquired more signatures. The quilt was hung in the Rhode Island State House during the 2018 and 2019 legislative sessions.
The Reproductive Privacy Act was passed in 2019 prohibiting “government interference in a woman’s decision to terminate a pregnancy ‘prior to fetal viability.’” Abortion beyond that point is ‘expressly prohibited except when necessary, in the medical judgment of the physician, to preserve the life or health of that individual.” In lay-terms, this is the codification of the federal Roe legislation at the State level.
*The spelling of “womxn” takes the place of the common spelling of woman. The reason is because The Womxn Project is signifying a more inclusive approach and the ‘x’ spelling not only raises awareness about the prejudice, discrimination, and institutional barriers womxn have face, but it is also part of a movement aimed at advancing what are seen as womxn’s rights within a human-rights based framework. This is done specifically in order to address the challenges faced by people living at the intersections. The use of this term is aimed at saying we want to meet the needs of womxn, but that we must also meet the needs of anyone pushed to the margins and limited by systems of oppression.
Collection information
The Womxn Project is a non-profit organization in Rhode Island focused on building a strong, feminist, community-based movement to further human rights of Rhode Islanders by using art and activism to advance education and social change. The Womxn Project stirs social awareness and invites political action to inclusively further womxn’s rights through creative advocacy campaigns and collaborative art projects. This collection contains records and items that were created to advocate for the passing of the Reproductive Privacy Act in 2019. Materials include canvassing packets, memorabilia, handmaid’s costumes worn at lobbying events at the Rhode Island Statehouse, community petition quilt squares, the community petition quilt, and petition scrolls that predated the quilt. Materials date from 1980-2019, though the bulk of the collection dates from 2017-2019. This collection is arranged into one series alphabetically by record type.
There are no restrictions on access, except that the collection can only be seen by prior appointment. Some materials may be stored off-site and cannot be produced on the same day on which they are requested.
This collection is arranged into 1 series.
Administrative information
Gift of the Womxn Project in 2019.
- Canvassing packet: contains mailing lists, May 23, 2019 (Box 1)
- Canvassing packet: contains mailing lists and postcards (1 of 2), May 24, 2019 (Box 1)
- Canvassing packet: contains mailing lists and postcards (2 of 2), May 24, 2019 (Box 1)
- Canvassing packet: contains mailing lists, postcards, and stamps, May 24, 2019 (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1982, 2017, 2019 (Box 1)
- Community petition quilt: quilt squares signed by individuals who supported Rhode Island's Reproductive Privacy Act, 2017 - 2019
  This item will be available soon. Please email pembroke_archives@brown.edu for more information.
- Community petition quilt square pattern and directions, circa 2018 (Box 1)
- Community petition quilt squares: quilt squares signed by individuals who supported Rhode Island's Reproductive Privacy Act [these did not get sewn onto the quilt], circa 2018 (Box 2)
- Correspondence from Rachel Cohen to neighbors re: calling Senate President in support of the Reproductive Health Care Act, November 9, 2018 (Box 1)
- Hand fan with logo and text, "the time is now #REPRO4RI", circa 2018 (Box 1)
- Handmaids costume: red floor-length cloak with white bonnet [NOTE: Developed by the author Margaret Atwood in the 1985 dystopian novel, The Handmaid's Tale, these fictional handmaids are women who are sexual servants forced to have children for others.] (1 of 2), 2019
- Handmaids costume: red floor-length cloak with white bonnet [NOTE: Developed by the author Margaret Atwood in the 1985 dystopian novel, The Handmaid's Tale, these fictional handmaids are women who are sexual servants forced to have children for others.] (2 of 2), 2019
- Memorabilia: buttons with logo and text, "the womxn project educate art act", circa 2018 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia: emergency contraceptive, 2019 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia: stamp of logo, circa 2018 (Box 3)
- Memorabilia: t-shirt with text, "controlling my body controlling my future" (1 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 3)
- Memorabilia: t-shirt with text, "controlling my body controlling my future" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 3)
- Petition scroll (oversize): signatures and notes from individuals to demonstrate support of Rhode Island's Reproductive Privacy Act (1 of 2), circa 2018
- Petition scroll (oversize): signatures and notes from individuals to demonstrate support of Rhode Island's Reproductive Privacy Act (2 of 2), circa 2018
- Postcards: postcards with various images used to send to voters to advocate for Rhode Island's Reproductive Privacy Act, circa 2018 (Box 3)
- Poster (oversize): poster with handmaid figure with text, "do not let this happen", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with handmaid figure with text, "the handmaids are messengers from a future where the U.S. is ruled by a fundamentalist regime and womxn are the property of the state", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with illustration of faceless people holding sign with text, "this fight isn't over!!! #REPRO4RI" (1 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with illustration of faceless people holding sign with text, "this fight isn't over!!! #REPRO4RI" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with illustration of power fist with text, "The Woman Project Celebrate Educate Act" (1 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with illustration of power fist with text, "The Woman Project Celebrate Educate Act" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with illustration of screaming person with text, "Let it out #REPRO4RI", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with images of community petition quilt and square and text, "Community petition quilt sign a signature square", circa 2018 (Box 4)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Adam Satchell, and text, "Thank you Senator Adam Satchell" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Adam Satchell, and text, "Thank you Senator Adam Satchell" (1 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Bridget Valverde, and text, "Thank you Senator Bridget Valverde" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Bridget Valverde, and text, "Thank you Senator Bridget Valverde" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Cindy Coyne, and text, "Thank you Senator Cindy Coyne", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Dawn Euer, and text, "Thank you Senator Dawn Euer" (1 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Dawn Euer, and text, "Thank you Senator Dawn Euer" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Donna Nesslebush, and text, "Thank you Senator Donna Nesslebush", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Erin Lynch-Prata, and text, "Thank you Senator Erin Lynch-Prata", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of James Seventy, and text, "Thank you Senator James Seventy" (1 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of James Seventy, and text, "Thank you Senator James Seventy" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of James Sheehan, and text, "Thank you Senator James Sheehan", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Josh Miller, and text, "Thank you Senator Josh Miller", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Mark McKenney, and text, "Thank you Senator Mark McKenney" (1 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Mark McKenney, and text, "Thank you Senator Mark McKenney" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Melissa Murray, and text, "Thank you Senator Melissa Murray", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Ryan Pearson, and text, "Thank you Senator Ryan Pearson", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Sam Bell, and text, "Thank you Senator Sam Bell", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Sandra Cano, and text, "Thank you Senator Sandra Cano", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Sue Sosnowski, and text, "Thank you Senator Sue Sosnowski" (1 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Sue Sosnowski, and text, "Thank you Senator Sue Sosnowski" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of Valerie Lawson, and text, "Thank you Senator Valerie Lawson", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo, image of William Conley, and text, "Thank you Senator William Conley", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo and text, "71% of Rhode Islanders support the Reproductive Health Care Act I'm one of them!" (1 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo and text, "71% of Rhode Islanders support the Reproductive Health Care Act I'm one of them!" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with logo and text, "honk! If you want to protect the right to abortion", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with text, "Protect safe, legal abortion", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with text, "Choose choice, no forced birth", circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with text, "See you Thursday let's make history together!" (1 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): poster with text, "See you Thursday let's make history together!" (2 of 2), circa 2018 (Box 5)
- Poster (oversize): Poster with text, "Stop HLA: a message to President Regan and the Members of the 97th Congress" and "we, the undersigned, urge you to oppose any and all bills or amendments to the United States constitution that would outlaw birth control methods used by millions for women and ould destroy a woman's right to a safe and legal abortion" followed by names, circa 1982 (Box 4)
- Posters with various messages that advocate for Rhode Island's Reproductive Privacy Act and stickers of the Womxn Project logo, circa 2018 (Box 3)
- Print material: contains Planned Parenthood newsletter and "The Vagina Monologues" program, 2018 (Box 3)